<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True and perfect relation of the nevves sent from Amsterdam, the 21. of February, 1603 concerning the fight of fiue Dutche shippes in the East Indies, against the Portugall fleete, consisting of eight great gallions, and 22. galleyes both great and small, wherof was Admirall, Don Andreas Fartado Mendosa : wherevnto is added also, the voyage and nauigation of the said fiue Dutche shippes and others, in the iles of East Indies, and of their comming home.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18445.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4397</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24292451</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24292451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08076)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1822:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True and perfect relation of the nevves sent from Amsterdam, the 21. of February, 1603 concerning the fight of fiue Dutche shippes in the East Indies, against the Portugall fleete, consisting of eight great gallions, and 22. galleyes both great and small, wherof was Admirall, Don Andreas Fartado Mendosa : wherevnto is added also, the voyage and nauigation of the said fiue Dutche shippes and others, in the iles of East Indies, and of their comming home.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T.C. for Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at the little shop ioyning to the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: A true and particular relation of the newes sent from Amsterdam, the 21. of February, anno. 1603.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Page 3 misnumbered as 1.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History, Naval.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
               <term>Portugal --  History, Naval.</term>
               <term>Portugal --  History --  Spanish dynasty, 1580-1640.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27496:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True and perfect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Newes ſent from <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the 21. of February, 1603. Concerning the fight of fiue Dutche ſhippes in the Eaſt Indies, againſt the Portugall Fleete, conſiſting of eight great Gallions, and 22. Galleyes both great and ſmall: wherof was Admirall, <hi>Don Andreas Fartado Mendoſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherevnto is added alſo, the Voyage and Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>of the ſaid fiue Dutche ſhippes and others, in the Iles of Eaſt Indies, and of their comming home.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Creede, featuring the personification of Truth being scourged by a hand from the clouds (McKerrow 299)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>VIRESSIT VVLNERE VERITAS</q>
               </head>
               <p>T C</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by T.C. for Thomas Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and are to be ſold at the little ſhop ioyning to the Exchange. 1603.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:27496:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27496:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE AND particular relation of the Newes ſent from <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the 21. of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary, Anno. 1603. <hi>Stilo nouo,</hi> concerning the fight of fiue Dutche ſhippes, in the Eaſt Indies, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Portugall Fleete, conſiſting of eight great Gallions, and 22. Galleyes, both great and ſmall: whereof was Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall <hi>Don Andreas Fartado Mendoſa.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, I haue hitherto ſignified vnto you thoſe Newes (whiche I had heard of ſundrie perſons) brought by the Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace from the Eaſt Indies, but now, foraſmuch as the Maiſter of the Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace himſelfe (called <hi>Cornelis Schon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein</hi>) arriued here yeſternight, certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying vs of all by word of mouth, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue written vnto you more certainly and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereof. To wit. That the fiue ſhippes which ſayled and departed hence, in the yeare 1601. on the 23. day of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill (whereof was Admirall <hi>Wollfert Hermans,</hi>) arriued in the ſtreight of <hi>Sunda,</hi> on Chriſtmas day, in the ſaide yeare 1601. where they were aduertiſed and warranted by a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27496:3"/> ſmall <hi>Chiniſh</hi> Shippe, that before <hi>Bantam</hi> laie a Portingall Armade or Nauie, conteining eight great Galleons, and 22. Galleyes, great and ſmall, which had laine before the Towne a day or two.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Dutche Admirall cauſed his ſaid fiue ſhippes to caſt Anker, and tooke counſell together for their better reſolution in their buſineſſe. And becauſe you may knowe what, and how many ſhippes they had in companie to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſuch, and ſo great an enterpriſe, I will rehearſe and ſet downe their names, and burthen of the ſame.</p>
            <list>
               <item>One ſhippe of the burthen of 520. tunnes, called <hi>Guelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One ſhippe of the burthen of 400. tunnes, called the <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One ſhippe of the burthen of 240. tunnes, called <hi>Vtrecht.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One ſhippe of the burthen of 120. tunnes, called the <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>One ſhippe of the burthen of 50. tunnes, called the <hi>Doue.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Their reſolution was, that they ſhould aſſaile and fight with the ſaid Armade or Nauie with their Ordinance: In handling whereof, our men apter, and farre better practiſed then the Portingalles, determining ſo to chaſe them from their ſiege: wherevpon they ſet ſayle, and the next day early in the morning, they beganne to fight with the Portingales ſhippes, and ſo with great force and reſolution on both ſides, they maintained this maner of fight with their Ordinance, not only the ſame whole day, but 6. or 7. dayes after, vntill the firſt day of Ianuary in the yeare 1602. and tooke the ſame time from the ſaid Portingales, two Galleyes, and thrée Galleyes which were wonderfully battered and briu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the ſhot of our fiue ſhippes.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:27496:3"/>
            <p>After that they themſelues had ſet them on fire, ſuffering them to driue downe the Riuer vpon our ſhippes, meaning thereby to hinder or rather to burne our ſhippes, but God be praiſed they effected no hurt at all.</p>
            <p>Finally, the Portingalles ſéeing no good iſſue like to fall on their ſide, left their ſiege of <hi>Bantam,</hi> and departed to the Ile of <hi>Ambona,</hi> on the one ſide whereof, they haue a Caſtle, which they ſtrongly fortified, and haue cut downe all the Cloues Trées, and pulled them vp by the rootes, or at the leaſtwiſe deſtroied as many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trees as they could, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting likewiſe a moſt great, wicked, terrible, and cruell mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the poore inhabitants of the ſame Ile, the right na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and condition of Tyrants, which are accuſtomed to vſe crueltie vpon poore diſarmed men and naked creatures, when they dare not defend, nor reuenge themſelues vpon their enemies. This is the great credit which this victorious <hi>Don Andreas Fartado Mendoſa</hi> with his Armade or Nauie hath gotten.</p>
            <p>Truly, it is onely the Lorde God which gaue ſo great courage and magnanimitie to the hearts of our people, with ſo ſmall a power of weake men to aſſaile and ouerthrow ſo great and mightie a Fléete in compariſon of ours, to which mercifull, louing, and omnipotent God, be all laude, praiſe and glorie. Amen.</p>
            <p>Our ſhippes remained nine dayes at <hi>Bantam,</hi> proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues of all neceſſaries, where they were wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and with great ioy and gladneſſe, receiued both great and ſmall, the reaſon thereof was, becauſe they thought that the Portingalles were determined to come vpon them, or at leaſt to build a Caſtle vpon an Ile, hard by <hi>Bantam,</hi> but the Lord hath confounded their deſſeignes.</p>
            <p>Our ſaide ſhippes being appointed to make their voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to <hi>Banda</hi> and <hi>Terrenata,</hi> for the remainder of the old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27496:4"/> furthered their voiage towards the ſame Iles, where they found and ſawe the cruell actions of the Portingalles, as committed by the ſaide Portingall Fléete in the Ile of <hi>Aubona,</hi> and were departed thence to <hi>Intidor,</hi> where they alſo haue a Caſtle. And howbeit the Ile of <hi>Aubona</hi> is ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate betwéene <hi>Terrenata</hi> and <hi>Banda,</hi> yet notwithſtanding our ſhippes ſeperated themſelues, the better to furniſh their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, whereof two directed their courſe for <hi>Banda,</hi> and thrée for <hi>Terreneta,</hi> where they found our Factor or Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Francis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erdoes</hi> in good health, being in great fauour with the King there, who ſhewed him all curteſie and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but he had not any great ſtore of Cloues, by reaſon that the yeare had bene verie vnſeaſonable and vnfruitfull, and yéelded but ſmall increaſe, as the like had not bene ſéene in many yeares before. They laded ſuch ſmal ſtore of cloues as they found there, and ſayled with the thrée ſhippes from thence towards <hi>Banda,</hi> to the other two, where they alſo found our Factor or Commiſſioner <hi>Adriaen <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>een,</hi> in good health, where one of the two ſhippes was alreadie fully la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with Nutmegges and Maces, alſo they laded there the ſhip called <hi>Guelderland,</hi> (which had bene in <hi>Terrenata</hi>) and the ſmall Pinnace the <hi>Doue,</hi> with which thrée ſhippes the Admirall <hi>Wollfert Hermans</hi> is now comming home. The Pinnace (being a little on the other ſide of <hi>Capo de buona Speranza</hi>) ſtraied, hauing loſt the company of the other two ſhippes, the <hi>Guelderland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> which we alſo daily do expect: They ſayled with theſe thrée ſhips from <hi>Bantam,</hi> on the 25. day of Auguſt. The other two ſhips, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> and the <hi>Wachſter,</hi> vnder the commaund of the Viceadmirall <hi>Hans Bauwell,</hi> ſayled from <hi>Bantam</hi> towards <hi>Terrenata,</hi> to the ende to ſtaie there for the new increaſe of cloues, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therewith to lade the ſaid ſhippes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iacob van Neck,</hi> with his two ſhips, to wéete the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27496:4"/> and <hi>Der Goude,</hi> who we thought ſhould haue had their lading of Cloues in <hi>Terrenata,</hi> and had bin there long before the other ſhips, hath effected nothing, by reaſon of the great ſcarcitie of commodities. And whereas right ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, or hard by the Caſtle <hi>Tydoro,</hi> there laie two Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galles ſhips, and one <hi>Magelane</hi> ſhip called the <hi>Fayth,</hi> which they had taken before, the ſaid <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>an Neck</hi> purpoſed to driue the ſaide two Portingall ſhips from thence (I thinke at the requeſt and inſtance of the King of <hi>Terrenata,</hi>) but his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe ſuccéeded not very well, for he loſt 8. or 9. of his men, whereof <hi>Nicholas Corneliſon</hi> Maiſter of the ſhip <hi>Ter Goude,</hi> was one, and he himſelfe loſt thrée of his fingers of his right hand: he ſayled from thence towards a place called <hi>Patana,</hi> ſcituate after <hi>Cuda</hi> or <hi>Malaua,</hi> where he procured halfe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for one of his ſhips with Pepper, and was purpoſed to returne to <hi>Terrenata,</hi> or at leaſtwiſe ſend thither the ſhippe <hi>Ter Goude,</hi> to the ende to lade her with the great encreaſe of the new Cloues.</p>
            <p>The Admirall <hi>Iacob Van Heemskercke,</hi> who likewiſe ſayled out of theſe Countries on the 23. of Aprill, 1601. is arriued at <hi>Bantam</hi> with ſixe ſhips, and the ſeuenth (being the Viceadmirall, looſing the company of the other ſhips about the lyne) hath bene in <hi>Achein,</hi> and hath laden there ſome ſmall ſtore of Pepper, wherewith he ſayled towards <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> where he found his company of theſe ſeuen ſhips, (fiue being fully laden) departed from <hi>Bantam</hi> homewardes, the 11. of May, in the yeare 1602. which was long before theſe thrée came thence, they muſt be as we thinke in the Ile of S. <hi>Helena,</hi> becauſe they would not willingly fall vpon thoſe coaſtes in the winter ſeaſon: the Lorde graunt them a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous voyage and ſafe arriuall.</p>
            <p>The Admirall <hi>Iacob Van Heemskerke,</hi> is ſayled further off with the two other ſhips towards the Iles, to the end to ſéeke out Negotiation.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27496:5"/>
            <p>Of the two ſhippes which went towards <hi>China,</hi> there is no newes, but only that at <hi>Bantam</hi> was a ſpéech which is not good: to wit, That thoſe of <hi>China</hi> ſhould haue hanged 15. or 16. of our people which went there a ſhoare, but thereof is ſmall certaintie, we hope that the matter ſhall not be ſo badde.</p>
            <p>Of the ſhippes of <hi>Zealand</hi> is no certaintie, but only that there was a flying ſpéech of two ſhippes which were ſéene in the Iles, and therefore it is ſuppoſed that the two ſhippes of <hi>Zealand</hi> were there.</p>
            <p>Of the Engliſh and French ſhippes we haue no newes at all.</p>
            <p>The fiue ſhippes which ſayled and departed from <hi>Bantam</hi> towards theſe countries, on the 11. of May, 1602. are theſe following. <hi>Amſterdam, Horne, Enckhuyſen,</hi> the blacke <hi>Lyon,</hi> the gréene <hi>Lyon.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27496:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
